Katharine Asher Engel Papers, 1916-1957
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Katharine Asher Engel papers
1916-1957
Engel, Katharine Asher, 1898-1957
MS 55
2 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
President, National Council of Jewish Women; President, New York Council of Jewish Women; Civic leader. Papers include memorabilia, minutes, news clippings, reports, speech texts, and high school yearbook. Bulk of material dates from 1941-57 and consists of notes and texts of speeches given by Engel and material related to her tenure as President of the National Council of Jewish Women.
Biographical Note
Katharine Idalia Asher was born 27 October 1898. She was graduated from Smith College in 1920 and did graduate work in English at Oxford University from 1923 to 1924. She was alumnae class president for thirteen years and in 1950 received an honorary degree from Smith College. Engel held many offices in the National Council of Jewish Women, and was National President from 1949 to 1955. She was on the boards of several other organizations, including Self-Help for Emigres from Central Europe, and United Service for New Americans. In 1955 she was the only woman appointed to the New York State Committee on Refugees. Among the Jewish fundraising groups benefiting from her volunteer service were the United Jewish Appeal and the Federation of Jewish Philanthropies. Engel was an active member of numerous other groups, including the U.S. National Committee for UNESCO and the Advisory Committee for Women's Forces in Civil Defense. Engel was married to Irving Engel, an attorney and chairman of the Executive Committee of the American Jewish Committee. They had one daughter. Katharine Engel died 30 March 1957.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Katharine Engel Papers include memorabilia, minutes, news clippings, reports, speech texts, and high school yearbook. The bulk of the material dates from 1941-57 and consists of notes and texts of speeches given by Engel and material related to her tenure as President of the National Council of Jewish Women.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
Search Terms
Engel, Katharine Asher, 1898-1957; National Council of Jewish Women--History--Sources; Immigrants--United States--Biography--Sources; Jewish women--United States--Biography--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Additional material is located in Smith College Archives.
Contents List
- Personal (Box 1, Folder 1)
- American Jewish Committee Half-Century Banquet, New York City, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photographs (Box 1, Folder 3)
- National Council of Jewish Women
  - Articles and publications (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - President's reports, 1953, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reports, minutes, and miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Triennial conventions, 17th-21st, 1943-55 (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
- Speeches (Box 2)
  - Texts, 1952-55 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Note cards, 1941-55 (Box 2)
- Senior Class Book, New Haven High School, 1916 (Box 2)